[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford
University okay let's uh let's go back
to where we were the last time we were
talking about the metric of space today
what we're going to do is a little bit
of
geometry and then we're going to get
really into the Dynamics of cosmology
the Dynamics actually means how does the
scale factor we discussed the scale
factor last time how does it change with
time how does the universe grow or
Shrink or whatever it does how does that
uh take place with time in other words
what's the evolution equations which
govern How the Universe expands and if
it eventually contracts what uh how it
contracts those equations are known as
the F frw fredman Robertson Walker
equations uh other people have they're
really the fredman
equation
um and we're going to study them tonight
but we're not going to derive them
tonight from general relativity we're
going to derive them from Newton's
equations Newton's equations are enough
to get us
started and then later we'll see how it
fits together with the general theory of
relativity so
let's
begin
with the idea of flat space a geometry
oh well first of
all we're always going to assume unless
I State otherwise that the universe is
homogeneous and
isotropic if it's homogeneous and
isotropic and it changes with time then
Hubble's Law will always be
true Hubble's Law that velocity is
proportional to distance will always be
true whenever the universe is
homogeneous and
isotropic does that mean linearly
proportional yes distance now that's a
statement at a fixed time the constant
of proportionality the so-called Hubble
constant depends on time in general only
for very very special situations is the
constant proportionality constant
generally it's not
uh it's constant with respect to space
it doesn't vary from point to point
that's
homogeneity if you found different
regions of space expanding differently
you would say that space is not
homogeneous so when one says the Hubble
constant I I may sometimes lapse into
calling it the Hubble constant keep in
mind it is constant with respect to
position in space but not constant with
respect to position and time uh
all right let's uh let's um talk about
the metric of SpaceTime given that space
is flat can space three-dimensional
space be flat and space time itself be
curved the answer is yes if you have
a metric which is time
dependent which describes flat spatial
slices embedded in four-dimensional
space time where the space itself may be
expanding or Contracting in other words
the space may be thought of as a
infinite flat rubber
sheet but the Giants far away who are
holding this rubber sheet are pulling on
it in such a way as to expand it
contract it make it time dependent then
the SpaceTime itself is curved but we'll
come back to the curvature of SpaceTime
today I want to think about space itself
yeah is there any issue about the fact
that the measuring rods are expanding
too no the measuring rods are not
expanding but the coordinates the
coordinates are expand so objects are
not the the space in between the
molecules or whatever is not sort of
expanding enough to make the thing
expand
right
right right the
uh forces which hold meter sticks
together are far stronger than the
forces which are the forces due to
expansion and so the meter stick is
being held together in a way that uh
that is not expanding with
the uh background space but what is
happening is disconnected things like
galaxies which are far enough apart that
they don't feel strong gravitational
fields between one another they will be
separating all right so
objects which are large enough and
diffuse enough that they don't feel any
forces binding them
together those will expand with the
expansion but things like meter sticks
which are held together by strong
electric and magnetic and uh uh
electrical forces and other kinds of
forces those won't expand with the
ambient expansion of the
universe all right question you can't
model it though as a force between
points is that correct because otherwise
it be an acceleration you can you can
think of the expansion of the universe
as a small force
between points uh let's say between
atoms okay yes but a small Force imagine
a small additional Force imagine a meter
stick and now let's imagine a very small
very very small Force force of repulsion
very very small of repulsion between the
atoms what will it
do uh will it tear the meter stick apart
no it might cause the meter stick to
expand a little
bit well imagine for the moment a
uniform time independent small extra
repulsive force between atoms all it
will do is make the equilibrium position
between the atoms slightly different
it'll
cause like having a spring supposing I
have a spring connected to the wall and
it's a real good hard tight
spring so that in equilibrium that
spring is really small and then let's
add another small
Force pulling the spring away from the
wall just another small uniform Force
for example what will it do will it
cause this uh the uh the particle at the
end of the spring to fly off and go
flying off no what it'll do is it'll
just change the equilibrium position by
a little bit so small that you
can't well it depends of course on the
magnitude of the force versus the size
of the spring constant right right
that's right the forces due to expansion
are minute on the scale of ordinary U
ordinary matter far far far smaller by
many orders of magnitude smaller than
the interatomic forces and so that's
right they could not possibly be
measured in terms of a slight um
modification of the size of a meter
stick but would that wouldn't that Force
if there were if there if there were no
attraction between the things wouldn't
that produce an accelerated movement
apart accelerated or decelerated if
there was no forces between the objects
yes they would expand with the expansion
of the universe accelerate in our
universe which is an accelerated
Universe yes well if there's a force it
would seem as though unless the force is
changing it would seem as though forces
produce acceleration as I recall that's
right wait wait what did you say if
there is no Force then there's an
acceleration I'm just it's I'm just
asking if the force in fact if that's
the correct model
because a force would produce
acceleration all by
itself it's not just it's not like a
linear
growth
com right um You are right expansion by
itself doesn't create a force but some
kinds of expansion can be modeled in
terms of a force namely accelerated
expansion but we'll come to that let's
uh let's so our model of the world then
is there are meter sticks which don't
expand measured in meters and measured
in meter sticks the distance between
galaxies does
grow and we can imagine coordinates
which are embedded and expanding with
the galaxies we can also Imagine
coordinates which are not expanding they
turn out not to be as useful so in that
framework every
galaxy to the extent that the galaxies
don't have extra random what's called
peculiar motion to the extent that the
Universe uniformly
expands uh each Galaxy is located at a
particular value of the coordinates and
that never changes with time what does
change with
time is the meaning the relationship
between the coordinates and actual
distances measured in meters
that relationship is codified by the
scale
factor okay so let's begin then let's uh
let's we want to get somewhere tonight
so
let's very quickly say um if I have a
flat space which I can just
draw as a coordinate grid like that then
it has a metric let's call it d s squar
for spatial separation for
distance uh for space the s s is some
constant any constant will do let's call
it
a squared times
dx2 plus d y^ 2 plus d
z^2 where a is just a fixed number and
what does it stand for IT stand stands
for the distance measured in meters
between neighboring
points separated by a distance Delta x
equal 1 so if this distance not this
distance but this coordinate separation
is one unit on each side then a
represents the distance between
neighboring points on this
grid and it goes out here in front in
the metric
now if the universe is
expanding then the distance between
neighboring points on the grid will grow
with time and that means that a is now a
function of
time a is a function of
time and that's the that's the metric of
space that tells you the distance
between points at a a fixed instant of
time what about preer time let's go back
over here to the special theory of
relativity uh in ordinary special
relativity the proper
time between two neighboring points of
space
time is given by dt^
2 minus the spatial distance
squared minus we might as well just call
it the S
squared minus the space distance
squared that's the form that the metric
of SpaceTime
takes DT ^2 minus ds^
2 in ordinary special relativity we
usually write this uh depending if we if
we introduce the speed of light into the
story then this just becomes uh
minus uh
dx2 plus d y^ 2 plus dz^2
divided by
c^2 that's the usual metric of the
special theory of relativity and by
looking at this we would just read off
that ordinary special relativity
corresponds to a metric like the well
the space components of the metric as
the space components the s squ
look like this we would just say that a
was one over the speed of
light but now we're imagining that a can
change with
time when a changes with time we have a
Time dependence there and the metric of
SpaceTime now becomes D to^ squar is
equal to dt^
2 minus a of t^ 2
time the x^2 + the y^ 2 plus the
z^2 so the metric of
SpaceTime is first of all time
independent it doesn't depend on X the
coefficients of the metric don't depend
on position in space they only depend on
time that's the homogeneity of the
universe of course in detail the
universe isn't quite
homogeneous and so really this is an
idealization and we could represent this
by saying the metric
tensor G mu
new has the
form one in the time time place G or G
time time is one that's the coefficient
of one no off diagonal elements there
are no terms like dxdy or
dxdt all the other terms are Z all the
other off diagonal terms are zero and
the other terms on the diagonal are all
minus a^ 2 - a^ 2 - a^ 2 and that would
be the metric tensor or the components
of the metric tensor of this metrics
it's a very very simple metric it's
almost as simple as flat SpaceTime the
only thing is that the
relationship between the spatial measure
and the time is time dependent that's a
peculiar yeah okay we can draw we can
picture this
geometry the space-time geometry if we
like by imagining a Time
axis this is just a cartoon of
it and
now at some early
time the coordinate grid
might correspond to a fairly small
spacing between neighboring galaxies But
as time goes
on the same grid corresponds to larger
separations between
galaxies
and if the universe continues to expand
then the
grid would look like this this is just a
picture
to focus your eye on what's Happening as
time goes on the sheet of rubber is
expanding and so the actual distance
measured in meters or measure or
centimeters or whatever it's measured in
is expanding as time goes on but this
galaxy this is uh Alice's Galaxy over
here this is Bob's Galaxy over
here Alice and Bob remain
separated
by
one unit of
coordinate increasing units
of
meters but a fixed distance apart in
terms of the coordinates that we're
assigning this is the way we're
assigning coordinates
in such a way that each galaxy has the
same coordinate value throughout the
history of uh of the
evolution okay so this
picture goes with this
metric a is the actual distance between
neighboring points and as you can see
something rather dramatic happens if
a becomes zero in particular if a in the
past was Zero at some time that
effectively means that everything is
squashed on top of everything
else uh squashed in the sense that the
number of meters separating Alice's and
Bob's galaxies go to zero which means
Alice and Bob are squashed on top of
each other that's why one says that when
a goes to zero the density becomes
infinite so infinitely small a is
something to watch out for it means
everything is crammed on top of
everything else with infinite
density on the other hand as a gets big
that means the coordinate mesh in meas
in in units of um of meters gets huge
and it means everything is separating
and becoming more and more diffuse
the small small t
a whose T is that does that make any
difference no it doesn't make any
difference uh you mean by whose T no
okay so what do we mean by whose T you
mean which reference frame or do you
mean which units are we using the T but
if it were a t writing on a light beam
it would never
change right okay good good good um this
metric this form of a
metric is only true in one frame well
not quite only one frame of
reference this form of the metric you
can ask the question now um is this form
of the metric invariant under some
Transformations what coordinate frames
if for in
particular uh there are other
coordinates in which the metric has
exactly the same form for example if I
just rotate the
coordinates in other words that just
corresponds to rotating the direction of
X and Y and so forth the form of this
metric would not change and that's
because DX s + d y^ s plus dz^2 is
invariant under rotation on the other
hand if I tried to make a Lorent
transformation the form of this metric
would change there's only at every point
in space we're talking about a
particular velocity
a reference frame with a particular
velocity and what is that
velocity physically what does it
correspond
to it corresponds to the velocity of the
local
Galaxy all right so galaxies are moving
apart and we are following those local
galaxies with coordinates embedded in
the space and the assumption is in that
coordinate system the metric looks like
this in some other coordinate system
where you might be whizzing by the
galaxies or you might be rotating your
frame of reference might be rotating it
might be accelerating it might be doing
nothing more complicated than just
moving relative to the galaxies the the
behavior of this metric is
different right so in the in the
coordinate system which is moving with
the galaxies this is the form of the
metric yeah any other
yeah you wouldn't see it wouldn't be
isot that's right that's right so this
is the form of the metric in the frame
which in which uh the world is isotropic
it seems to me you ought to say it's
aging with the galaxies too you ought to
say it's aging with the galaxies too
well I don't know the coordinate frames
age I mean the the the time the time
Factor has
to what about this yeah that that
that's the one that that you have to
that has to be key to the Galaxy's age
it seems well each Galaxy carries clocks
with it exactly right and the clocks
measure this DT that's right that's
right this T is the time measured by a
clock moving the clock made in the
standard Cosmic clock Factory where
every clock was made out of the same
materials the same atomic clock for
example and this time is measuring the
time in the frame of
reference moving with the galaxies which
means it's the time each clock moving
with the Galaxy's measures yes in this
reference
frame the Galaxy's motion is DT equals
DT
yes that's right that's correct in this
reference frame time along the Galaxy
lines time along the world lines of a
galaxy
is the same as proper time along the
world lines of the Galaxy that's correct
corre that's why it's what clocks
measure that's why it is what clock's
measure yeah are there uh
Transformations that leave this form of
the metric invariant you know like the
Len transformation leaves the manowski
metric yeah there aren't very many
Transformations the this the presence of
material in the
universe namely
galaxies um how to say it breaks the
Symmetry and picks out a particular
frame of
reference right now physics in this
room is different because of our own
presence because of the material in the
[Music]
room the equations of particles moving
around for example would be different in
frames of reference that were moving
than in frames of reference that was
standing still for example in a frame of
reference which is moving rapidly
an object standing still in that frame
of reference okay so we have a frame of
reference which is moving rapidly
relative to you guys uh that's me I'm
moving rapidly and I start juggling do I
have to take into account my own motion
well the answer is in practice yes why
because the atmosphere is not moving
with me so if I move fast enough my uh
juggling uh devices uh juggling pins or
uh whatever they are are going to be
swept Along by the atmosphere uh empty
out the room completely and make a real
true
vacuum and then or cause the air to move
with me for some reason but best to just
remove the air and everything and make a
true vacuum then my rules for juggling
and the way I would juggle would be the
same in the moving reference frame so
it's the presence of actual
matter that affects the laws of physics
not the laws of physics but the rules
for juggling for example we have Toons
too right yes you'd have to remove
everything absolutely all right so in
this case it is the galaxies themselves
which which are creating the metric
remember Mass creates the
metric but if the galaxies are in a
particular frame of reference if they're
homogeneously distributed and isotropic
distributed then in that frame of
reference this must be the form of the
metric as was mentioned in another frame
of reference for example frame of
reference moving along the world would
not be
isotropic all right now
um what we're going to do is first begin
by studying Newtonian
cosmology Newtonian cosmology gets us a
long
way it
uh gets us to the basic laws of
cosmology to the basic laws by which the
scale factor changes with time now
remember you can either think of the
scale factor as something in general
relativity or you can just think about
it as the distance between the
neighboring
galaxies so let's take Newtonian
perspective on it completely Newtonian
and see if we can work out how a
Newtonian homogeneous and isotropic
universe would behave right see if we
can find out how the scale factor would
behave so what are we starting with
we're starting with a world I'm just
draw that's a little patch of the world
I can't draw the whole thing on the
Blackboard and the world is filled up
with a gas
a uniform
gas and of course that gas is not really
a gas of air molecules the gas points
are galaxies galaxies stars and so forth
um and it's pretty
uniform it's uniform enough on a large
scale that we can pretend that it's just
plain
uniform now let's take let's Place
ourselves who are we are we anybody
special we're going to find out that the
equations although we're going to write
them from our own perspective from the
perspective at
somebody
who in his own egotistical
imagination is at the center of the
universe we're going to find out that
the way the universe looks to us is
exactly the same way as it would look to
somebody else that anybody can call
themselves being at the center but let's
take the perspective that we are at the
center first of all and let's write some
equations oh before I do that what do we
do
here I seem to have lost a page of my
notes and in fact I jumped ahead of
myself
my my printer is a very
it's got a nasty little demon in it
which
uh mixes up pages and loses
them yes
right
what how do the motion of the galaxies
what determines it in a Newtonian Theory
well it's gravitation the gravitation
will tend to pull them together
that's basically what gravitation does
it's a pull it tends to pull things
together and before we actually enter
into cosmology it's worthwhile talking
first about the motion of ordinary
particles in the gravitational field of
a heavy Mass that's the starting point
that starting point is going to be
useful in studying the rest of the
universe so let's just step
back and think about a heavy Mass point
or a heavy Mass
here some Mass let's call it capital M
for the
moment capital M and imagine a second
Mass small
M which has been ejected by force by
some initial impulse initial impulse it
has been ejected away from the
gravitating earth for example or star or
whatever it happens to be it's been
ejected Away by an initial thrust but
then just simply allowed to ride the
gravitational field and do whatever
Newton says it should do well all we
need to know all we really need in order
to uh go through and work out the
cosmology
of in a few minutes is we need to know
energy conservation that's all that
really comes into the equations for
cosmology is energy conservation all
right
so what is the energy of this point Mass
which has been ejected away from this
heavy static object what is the energy
of it there are two kinds of energies
that it has kinetic and potential
kinetic energy what's the kinetic energy
of
this mv^ s masstimes its velocity
squared we're going to assume that the
velocity is radially outward this is not
correct there a
two this is small M this is the kinetic
energy of the outgoing Mass what about
its potential energy in the
gravitational field of the uh heavy
object here anybody
remember well it's got the product of
the
masses the product of the masses it's
got Newton's
constant divided by the distance I'm
going to call the distance between them
just D for
distance and am I missing
anything no no no no no no no no no no
the force contains the distance squared
the potential energy only contains the
distance okay not mg not mmmg / d^2
that's Force
energy the potential energy is just
product of M's G and distance that's all
one thing is missing out of this
negative
sign gravitational energy gravitational
potential energy is negative now
remember forces always push in the
direction to decrease potential energy
the gravitational field of the earth
pulls in a direction which decreases the
potential energy of this pin all right
so Force pushes you in direction of
decreasing potential
energy uh did I get
this sorry it's plus isn't it yeah yeah
yeah uh no it's it's minus it's minus
it's minus it's minus and it's minus
because it corresponds to the force
being attractive Force being attractive
makes it minus here uh putting this Mass
very close to the planet creates a large
amount of negative potential energy
putting it far away creates a smaller
amount of negative potential energy the
energy becomes more negative by pushing
towards here so that's why the potential
energy is negative for gravitation
corresponds to an attractive force and
that's it what does energy conservation
say it says that this energy doesn't
depend on time that's all there might be
many many different objects ejected
out from different positions for
example each one may have a different
energy when I say the energy is constant
I simply mean that the energy of this
particular particle doesn't change with
time so it's
constant let's just call it constant
all right now I want to play with this
equation a little
bit actually not so much for the time
being let's leave it the way it is now
we come back yeah the potential energy
increase with
distance yes yes yes let's see why
that's
true
okay first of all let's plot
1/ D let's forget the the constants here
let's forget all the constants
here let's plot the function 1/ D what
does the function 1/ D look like it
looks like this
correct it decreases at large
D you asked the question so nod your
head and answer if you understand okay
here's d 1/
d decreases with large D but what about
Min - 1 /d minus 1 /d is exactly the
same except upside down that's minus one
overd all right which way does the force
push it pushes toward decreasing
potential energy so it pushes if you
like
toward smaller distance or pulls
equivalently it pulls so an attractive
Force corresponds to a negative
potential energy like this all right so
this is
constant and this tells you some
information let's talk about the
different possibilities the energy let's
just call it energy for the moment we'll
just call it energy energy the energy
has three possibilities it could be
positive it could be negative or it
could be just plain zero those are the
only three
possibilities can the energy be positive
let's imagine again
the uh
the projectile being ejected away from
the surface of the Earth or something
like that well if the the potential
energy only depends on the distance from
the center of the earth D is the
distance from the center of the earth
that's fixed that's fixed let's say at
the surface of the Earth by making the
velocity sufficiently
large this term can easily be made to
overwhelm that term
all right just by making the velocity
sufficiently large in that case the
energy is positive it starts out
positive and it must remain positive
okay so yes positive energy is possible
what about negative energy well yes you
can have negative energy also supposing
the the starting velocity is very very
small even better let the starting
velocity be absolutely
zero then this term isn't there or it's
neg ible and the potential energy
dominates in that case for sufficiently
small velocity the energy is negative
can the energy be zero sure just make
sure that the velocity is just right to
cancel this term at the starting point
here just choose the Velocity in such a
way that these two are equal and then
the velocity is zero all right what what
is that particular velocity called that
matches these two
exactly that's the escape
Velocity if the velocity is smaller than
the escape Velocity let's plot let's
make a plot this is distance this is
time what happens to this
projectile well if the velocity is less
than the escape Velocity we know very
well what happens you just fall back
down to
earth so let's start at time T equals 0
and throw our Pro projectile up in the
air with a small velocity what happens
the distance begins to increase and then
it gets to the top of its trajectory and
falls back
down if we throw it with even less
velocity it falls down even more
quickly and doesn't rise as
high right what happens if we throw it
with a humongous velocity a huge
velocity huge enough velocity and the
energy is
positive in that case we know what
happens we simply get ejected completely
from the gravitational field of the
earth and starting with a large enough
velocity there's some pull inward toward
the surface of the Earth and so there is
some deceleration but it's not enough to
slow the spaceship or whatever it is
down the spaceship or projectile escapes
it escapes and eventually moves off with
a uni form velocity which means a
constant
slope somewhere in between these two
behaviors is exactly the right starting
velocity to make the Energy Zero if it
were any less the velocity you'd fall
back down if it were anymore you surely
Escape that velocity is just the
marginal separation point between
escaping and not escaping that is the
escape Velocity
and your distance just keeps increasing
and increasing and increasing but at an
Ever decreasing
rate so that's the escape Velocity this
is E equals
z this is e greater than zero and these
are e less than
zero all right that's the
basic decomposition of radial orbits
into bound orbits which fall back down
just at the escape Velocity where the
distance just gradually
increases but uh with a slowing velocity
the velocity slowing down but never
enough to make it turn around and then
positive energy where the projectile
moves off with a with a velocity which
doesn't get
smaller right the universe behaves the
same way or the equations of motion of
the universe have the same
property if the
initial starting point has the has all
of the galaxies moving outward relative
to each other according to the Hubble
law but with a big enough Hubble
constant in other words with a big
enough velocity relative velocity then
it will just shoot out
and the galaxies will all escape from
each other cleanly and with no uh no
tendency to fall back if the initial
outward velocity of recession is to
small then gravity will beat the outward
motion and they'll all fall back in a
giant
crunch the Big Bang will be followed by
a big crunch there is a
point with the starting values of the
Velocity which is like the escape
Velocity which is just barely enough for
the universe to keep expanding outward
now what I'm talking about now is
Newtonian cosmology Newtonian cosmology
there is a particular starting point for
the velocities where you will
do exactly the same thing as this
escaping particle in fact we can use
exactly this expression here MV ^2 / 2us
MMG / D equals a constant energy to
figure out exactly what happens to these
galaxies here and and the trick is
Newton's theorem let me remind you what
Newton's theorem
says Newton's theorem is a remarkable
theorem Newton discovered it
geometrically we discussed it I think
last quarter at length I'll just remind
you what it says it says that if you
have a spherically symmetric
distribution of matter in other words
think of yourself at a center well you
don't have to think if there is a center
and if about that Center the
distribution of mass is
isotropic to get homogeneous if it's
isotropic the same in every
direction okay then the gravitational
field the gravitational force let's
here's our here's our lump of matter
completely spherically
symmetric then
the force on a particle out here is
exactly the
same as if all of the mass were
concentrated at a point at the center
that's the first
statement all right but the statement is
a little stronger than that
supposing the point in question was
somewhere in the interior of this ball
of material the only restriction is that
the ball of material be spherically
symmetric then Newton's theorem says the
following it
says that you can
draw where are we yeah let's uh let's
draw this
carefully we have a distribution of
matter which is spherically symmetric it
doesn't have to be uniform it just has
to be isotropic relative to the
center and we place a particle over here
what is the gravitational force on that
particle and the answer is you draw a
sphere at the same radius as the
particle and you take all of the mass
inside that
sphere and you pretend that it was
localized right at the center of the
sphere what about the material outside
that
sphere Newton's theorem says that it
does not contribute to the force on a
particle in other words all the masses
at a distance larger than the particle
cancel out
when they contribute to the force of
that particle only the masses on the
interior closer than the particle
contribute to the force it's a
remarkable
theorem in particular it says something
that at first sight does not seem
terribly intuitive suppose you had a
perfect shell a perfect spherical shell
of
matter not uh not a ball a ball means
that it's filled up solidly but a shell
of
material a thin shell of material and
you put a p a particle at the center
what is the gravitational force on it
it's clearly zero because it doesn't
know which way to get pulled so to speak
what if you put it over
here it's also zero that's also zero the
force the force do you might think that
it gets pulled to the right because this
Mass over here is
closer okay but there's a lot more of
the mass far away the mass on this side
over here there's a lot of it the mass
to the right there's only a little bit
of it and they cancel what happens if we
look at the if we take the particle
outside the
shell what is the force on the particle
shell exactly the same as if the entire
shell were concentrated at a point
that's Newton's
theorem
uh the reference for it is the prinkipia
and you don't even need calculus for it
on the other hand not using calculus
makes it incred incredibly
difficult
okay the story is I I don't know I don't
know what the actual truth of it is but
uh that that Newton of course invented
the calculus for purposes like this
worked these things out using calculus
but of course he knew that all his uh
compatriots uh compatriots his his all
his enemies didn't know calculus and so
in order to convince them of the truth
of his theory he worked out everything
using only ukian
geometry and uh that's why the prinkipia
is so hard to
read uh but uh yes okay this is a
theorem all right now let's pick then
let's pick just for Simplicity let's
pick a Galaxy or a mass moving with the
galaxies let's pick it along the x-axis
although that's not important since
everything is isotropic it doesn't
matter which axis we pick but let's pick
our Mass along the x axis and it's at
coordinate
X let's work out Newton's equations yes
what's the meaning of spherical symmetry
in an ISO in a
homogeneous
distribution well it means anybody looks
around and sees everything the same in
every direction no not isotropic
homogeneous I at what is the meaning of
homogeneous well I'm just saying at the
moment I'm not using homogeneous but I
will well I'm just having trouble
visualizing what what the shells would
be in a homogeneous Universe cuz sort of
I don't know what to
neglect well so far I haven't introduced
any shell into this okay will but so not
yet yeah MH yes in in the example you
gave there should we be a little
surprised that it seems like has the
particle moves across the boundary the
force is
discontinuous I don't know if you should
be surprised it's a true statement of
course um boundaries are not really
infinitely thin they do really have a
distribution a shell of course has some
thickness and so everything would vary
continuously but you know if you had a
very very thin shell yes the uh the
force would vary
discontinuously should you be surprised
um yeah I would say yes you should be
surprised uh uh it's a little it is a
little bit surprising of course when you
think about it enough and you work out
the equations and you get familiar with
it it's less
surprising uh and
uh it's it's it's incidentally very
special to the 1 over R squ Newtonian
Force law it would not be true with
other Force laws other Force laws do not
have this property this is the 1 / R 2
Force law has this property all right
um I'll tell you what the mathematics of
it is the mathematics is fairly simple
and or a picture of what's
Happening um if you imagine if you
imagine a mass point is instead of a
mass Point imagine that it is a flow of
water
which is materializing at this point it
could be coming in from behind the
Blackboard a little pipe ending here and
the flow of water flows
outward outward in the plane of the uh
how does the how does the velocity of
the flow decrease with distance well it
decreases
with in two Dimensions it's one over R
in three dimensions it's one of R squ so
in three dimensions in other words if at
some point of the World a flow of water
flowed out away from some point the
velocity field would be 1 / r
s okay now
imagine
that we put one of these little
spouts at each point around the circle
continuously so that around on the
circle here the uh uh there was a
continuous distribution of flow of water
out of that
Circle
right what the water completely fills
everything but what is the velocity of
the water in different places well on
the outside of the Ring the velocity is
Flowing outward and it flows outward
with a velocity that's exactly the same
as if the same flow of water
materialized at the center but what
about inside this circle can there be
any flow of water which direction would
it flow in if it flew flew out
radially where would it be coming from
supposing the water flowed out
here how could that be if there was no
Source at the
center how could it possibly be that
there would be water flowing away from
the center if there was no source of
water at the center
right that's essentially so so the
answer is that in the interior of this
shell of sources of water there would be
no flow it would stand perfectly still
but the center you move the second you
move to the other side you would see a
flow which is exactly the same as if all
the source were concentrated at the
center if you think about that for a
little while you'll get the reason why
um why the one of R squ Force has this
surprising n tonian property but we not
our purpose tonight is not to derive it
we discussed it earlier in the class I
think we even derived it we're going to
use it we're going to use it to study
cosmology and to use it to to study
cosmology we just pick a point away from
the
center the center being arbitrary but
nevertheless pick a
center in the frame of reference where
the center is at rest right at the
center where this blue Galaxy here is at
rest pick that point and we'll apply
Newton's equations to another second
point which is a coordinate X relative
to this is xal 0 over
here and this is x equals whatever it is
over here all right so how do we find
the force on this particle over here
well well what we do is we draw a sphere
knowing that everything is
isotropic we can draw a
sphere centered at xal
0 and using Newton's theorem Newton's
theorem tells us that the force in this
frame of reference at rest with respect
to this galaxy the force
on the other Galaxy over here is exactly
the same as if all the mass on the
interior of this red shell were
concentrated right at x equals z and all
the other galaxies on the outside don't
exert any force on
it in other words for a Galaxy at point
x it behaves exactly as if the entire
Mass within it within this sphere will
concentrated at the center and as if
there were no other Mass on the
outside so let's for the moment call the
mass
concentrated within this sphere and
notice the sphere grows as if X
increases of course the sphere will grow
with x the sphere always surrounds the
same number of galaxies if the galaxies
are separating apart the sphere grows
that sphere always contains the same
number of galaxies and therefore the
same total mass
so let's call the mass within that
sphere capital M for the moment it's the
mass within that sphere then the motion
of this point follows exactly the same
law where is it we erased it off the
Blackboard let me write it out
again
12 m v^ 2 where V e is the outward
velocity of this
point minus capital M little m g over
the
distance is equal to something which is
fixed with
time all right fixed with time does not
change with time for that particular
Galaxy let's just call
it the energy or let's just call it a
constant
all right just to save myself uh some
confusion later not confusion but just
to save some uh some steps let's
multiply this equation by two and it
just becomes mv^
2us 2 m little m g d is equal to twice a
constant but twice a constant is just
another
constant so the way I've written it here
with the two here is exactly the same
equation that I wrote before okay all we
have to do to implement this equation is
find out to try to figure out what the
velocity of this particle at point x
is and here is where the Hubble law
comes
in what does the Hubble law tell us well
even before the Hubble law yes all
right let's begin not with the Hubble
law but with the actual physical
distance
I suppose we should give these galaxies
name again names Bob and
Alice Bob thinks of himself at rest and
he sees Alice moving
away the distance to Alice is
equal to X but not x x has to be
multiplied by something a the scale
factor as a function of
time what about Alice's velocity
relative to Bob that's velocity that's
equal to the time derivative of
D now does X Change with time no X is
just the coordinate fixed embedded
inside Alice moves with Alice so X does
not change with time but a can change
with time that's equal to X time a DOT
of t
let's use that in this equation over
here for this particular Galaxy this is
all we need M oh incidentally yes let's
go one step further before we move to
this board let's go back to this board
and let's divide by the
mass of the uh projectile
particle the mass of the projectile
particle is also a constant
that means the constant divided M here M
appeared in both these terms here and
the right hand side was just a constant
a constant meant constant with
time what is a constant divided by m
it's also a
constant so I can just call it constant
I don't need to write constant over M
all I need to remember is that the left
hand side does not change with time it's
equal to something which is constant
with time time when I say constant with
time I don't necessarily yeah constant
with time okay let's let's plug in here
and see what we get the square of the
Velocity that's the uh that's the first
term here velocity
squared velocity squared that's X
sared that's fixed that's constant
times the square of the time derivative
of the scale
factor remember what we're trying to do
we're trying to figure out how the scale
factor changes with time well a DOT is
how the scale factor changes with time
so far we don't have an equation for it
I've just written down a DOT there's
also X squ here which depends on which
Galaxy we're talking about different
galaxies different
X's okay now let's write down this term
minus twice
G the
distance is x *
a but what about the mass within
here the mass in here is not some just a
number like the mass of the Sun it
depends on how big this sphere is how
big it depends on how many galaxies are
inside it it depends dep on how many
galaxies are inside it basically the
number of galaxies inside that sphere
stays fixed with time because the sphere
grows with the galaxies it's fixed to
pass through Alice here as Alice moves
away the sphere grows but the galaxies
don't move out of that sphere they stay
inside that Sphere for all time and so
the mass within that sphere stays fixed
with
time but depending on which sphere we
were to take
this sphere or this sphere that mass
would change so here's how we figure out
the mass we say supposing using the idea
that the universe is
homogeneous we say there's a there is a
well defined at every instant of time
there is a well defined mass per unit
volume a
density okay a mass per unit volume
density so in order to find out the mass
in the sphere we need need to take the
density let's call it
row row is the density the number of
kilograms per unit uh cubic meter for
example row is density let's write it
here row equals mass
density and what do we multiply it by in
order to get the uh the mass within the
sphere we right the volume of the sphere
you jumped ahead of me right the volume
of the sphere and the volume of a sphere
is
4/3
pi
H
um no not yeah X cubed a cubed x cubed *
a
cub d d cubed if you like right d cubed
which is X cubed a
cubed all right so 4/3
or
yeah so let's put it together let's
combine so it's a mess but let's put it
together oh sorry we have the right hand
side the right hand side equals a
constant
okay any questions
say it again changes with time row
indeed changes with time and we're going
to worry about row changes with time why
does row change with
time yeah because the galaxies separate
and so it becomes less dense with time
but at any given time this is It's the
density that goes here okay this term
has an X squ in front of
it oh oh one other thing row may depend
on time but it doesn't depend on
position in space so it doesn't why
what's what principle is involved there
homogeneity so it doesn't depend on
which X we're talking about but it does
depend on time all
right now let's uh simplify X Cub a cub
over x a that's just X2 a a s right
notice that both of these
terms contain X
SAR the other thing the other things
that it contains do not depend on where
you are which Galaxy you're talking
about a is the scale factor that's the
same everywhere G is Newton's constant
that's the same everywhere row is
assumed to be the same everywhere
certainly four three and Pi are the same
everywhere the only thing that vares
from place to place here here here is
X so the left hand side is proportional
to X
SAR that must mean that the right hand
side must be proportional to x squar no
wait a minute I said it's
constant how can it how can it depend on
X
squ what did I mean by constant I meant
that it doesn't change with time for
each X it doesn't depend on time but in
order for this equation to make sense
this constant must also be proportional
to X2 so that means in order for the
equation to make sense the
energy
of and that remember the right hand side
is related to the energy the energy of
more distant
particles must be larger than the energy
of a closer ones but that makes sense of
course it does they're moving faster so
this constant what I called constant
over here is really a constant with
respect to time times x squared
otherwise the equations couldn't make
sense once we assume that once we assume
that the equations make sense then you
can divide away
X2 and notice what you have and this
this constant now is a constant both
with respect to space and time
what goes over
here okay now we have something
interesting we have an equation which
doesn't depend on which Galaxy we
started with it does and which Galaxy
we're talking about I could have put us
at the center and studied Alice's
Galaxy or Fred's Galaxy or Michelle's
Galaxy
or George's Galaxy oh George's Galaxy
out there anybody's
Gala anybody's Galaxy we like we would
get exactly the same
equation the me it depends on a it
depends on time so it's an equation for
a as a function of time but it doesn't
depend on which Galaxy we started with
as the center or which Galaxy we studied
as the one moving relative to the center
so we've managed
to invoke a set of assumptions which
gives us a simple clean equation for the
way a varies with time now it depends on
this constant on the right hand side it
depends on the constant at the right
hand side just in order to put it in a
more standard form I'm going to put it
in a more standard form
now standard simply means historically
standard form uh standard form involves
transposing this piece to the
right and dividing the whole equation by
a squared so let's do
that if we divide by a 2 we have a DOT 2
over a
s
equals I'm transposing this to the right
equals 8 Pi G over
3 8 2 * 4 piun 3 8 Pi G over
3 Row the density of
mass that's all from that term that's it
right plus and on the right hand side
plus constant I'm now going to call that
constant minus K now is it does that
mean that the constant is negative no it
could be positive or negative or that is
to say minus K could be either positive
or negative so or zero I have not biased
it by writing minus K here uh there's
nothing special about K being positive
or negative it's a a historical
terminology K here can be positive
negative or zero and divided by a
s where did the a squ come from it came
from the fact that I divided the
equation by a
squ these are very famous equations in
cosmology they're called the f W
equation with these equations this
equation is called the F frw fredman
Robertson Walker Freedman is spelled
with one e and one
i f r e i d m an Alexander
fredman uh and who Robertson and Walker
are I don't know uh they were Johnny K
ly's in the business I don't know how
they got into it but there was Alexander
Friedman shortly very shortly after
Einstein uh he derived it from the from
the general theory of
relativity I don't know why these
equations weren't derived by
Newton
um Newton wanted the universe to be
static and eternal and stay there
forever and ever and uh he made some
mistakes along the way in order to uh he
actually he didn't make mistakes he just
thought it should be and knew there was
something wrong with his own
equations um no knew there was something
wrong even with his equations or his
assumption in any case what does this
equation tell you it tells you that if
there's any mass density
here uh in general unless these two
exactly cancel but they can't they won't
they won't cancel in general these two
that a will depend on time the left-and
side in general won't be zero and it'll
depend on time and that means the
universe will either expand or contract
or whatever it's supposed to do
these are the F frw equations now the
problem is supposing I sent you home to
solve this equation the first thing you
would tell me it would ask me I think is
what is row can we just put a number in
for row what's the what's the um anybody
have any idea at all what
the density of material average material
in the universe is
today I I don't I just wonder if anybody
does uh told us there was about one
proton I I think it's more like about 50
but uh uh but you know it's a small
number of protons per cubic meter it's a
very very small number but that's okay a
small number is all right but it's not
time independent it won't stay that way
as things expand the density will
decrease as the density decreases what
goes in here will depend on the scale
factor so there's a hidden dependence as
equation here involving the time
derivative and so forth but there's a
hidden dependence on the scale factor
here that we have to unravel if we want
to solve this equation another thing we
have to decide is what value of K to put
in there now remember when you went
remember now K was like the energy of
this particle that was ejected away from
you it could be positive negative or
zero yeah actually function only M was
not
M yeah
yeah
yeah yeah yeah I went through you're
telling me I went through what is
essentially an extra step of introducing
row I did it yes you're right I could
have used M ided by
volume okay um I didn't do that because
uh because I wanted to put it in a
standard I wanted you to get familiar
with this particular form of the
equation which depends on the density
all right the other thing one has to
decide is what about K it's a constant
but it could be positive negative or
zero let me remind you what that means
well if minus K is positive it means
it's like the situation where the
particle is receding with greater than
the escape Velocity in that case the
universe just continues to expand
forever and ever doesn't slow
down there may be some initial
deceleration for the same reason that if
you shoot something away from the
earth at first it will decelerate
because it's being pulled but as it gets
further and further from the earth the
pullback becomes more and more
diminished and it'll just shoot off with
a more or less uniform
velocity okay so if K if minus K is
positive that corresponds to the
positive energy situation the universe
just continues to grow and
uh gravity eventually becomes irrelevant
and everything shoots apart with uniform
velocity or uniform that's number one
number two we have to do something about
figuring out how to express row but the
only other thing I wanted to point out
is that this a do over
a it's actually squared over here but
the last time I told you another name
for a do over
a a do over a was the Hubble
constant which is in constant with time
it was the Hubble constant so another
way to write this is that the Hubble
constant
squ is equal to 8 Pi G * the density of
material-
K is row proportional to 1 R 1X CU
here one
yeah you got rid of how how did you get
rid of the
X in the
equation dividing by
it
X2
X2 and also the other term which I've
erased off
here the constant
term I said has to be proportional to X2
if the equations are to make sense if
the left hand side is proportional to X
squ the right hand side must also but
you can kind of check
it you can um you can check the fact
that as you move away if the Hubble law
is satisfied then obviously the further
away you are the faster you're moving
and so the energy will depend on where
you are and it will depend on it in the
right way to make this X squ over
here we just got rid of the x s by the
Y does the U does the constant have
units we start out with energy but we we
canceled out
this squ constant in this form does not
have
units uh again let's I'm going to assume
the speed of light is equal to one what
are the units of
a meters or length length what are what
is the you what is
um oh I'm sorry yeah no no that's right
that's right that's right what about the
the the dot what are the units of Dot
a
DOT is length over
time all right now in units in which the
speed of light is equal to one length
over time is dimensionless if we measure
space the same way we measure time then
a DOT is
dimensionless and the left hand side has
units of 1 / a squ one over length
squared here's a one over length squar
here so that means that K is
dimensionless K is dimensionless has no
Dimensions you can check
that this thing has the same units over
here but let's talk now about row what
do we know about
row well let's take let's
take a cubic cell of
space and now let's let it be one unit
of
coordinate on a
side a cube of space
a unit cube
where X is equal to
1 Y is equal to
1 and Z is equal to one so it's a cube
it's not it's not a cubic meter in size
it's just a cube in coordinate space one
unit on a side and let's suppose that
there is a mass m inside
it okay so in a
cubic coordinate volume one coordinate
unit on a side let's suppose there's a
total mass
m how much mass will be there later in
that same
Cube the same amount because the cube
corresponds to an expanding Cube the
galaxies expand the galaxies don't
expand but the difference between
expands the number of galaxies in there
stays the same and so that mass is fixed
and stays the same for all time what is
the density the density is the mass
divided by the
volume
okay there the mass in there divided by
the volume what is the
volume a
cubed so that's row
now in terms of M we of course have to
know at some point in time we have to
know what the mass inside a cubic volume
a cubic volume is that's a parameter
there are a number of parameters that go
into here which are numerical parameters
which determine the behavior
thereafter we uh we don't get we don't
get a completely free lunch here
yeah to that
yeah
mhm that's why I keep telling you the
constant is not a
constant function Ro and R
changes right the H constant is not a
constant
[Music]
the final examination is going to
consist of one question is the Hubble
constant a
constant that's right the left hand side
is not constant and the right hand side
is not
constant all right um choices that have
to be made the amount of mass in a cubic
unit
volume where the K is zero positive
positive or negative and what its value
is and that's about it that's about the
only arbitrary things in this here all
right k equals 0 corresponds to the
universe being exactly at the escape
Velocity if things were shot out a
little bit
slower things would crunch a little bit
faster they would just recede off and at
k k equals z they just move away but at
an Ever diminishing
velocity now keep in mind this at this
stage is a Model A Newtonian model of a
cosmology it doesn't contain yet certain
features that the real thing has yeah if
k equals z then the velocity between two
galaxies is approaching zero and is it
approaching zero in in such a way so
that the distance between them is
bounded or Unbound
unbounded unbounded same as the particle
being ejected from the
earth it
slowly no no it couldn't possibly come
to a rest if it actually at some finite
time came to rest it would fall back in
so it slowing down it slows down yeah
right it slows down but with the
distance ever increasing but more and
more slowly so the velocity goes to zero
but the distance does not not go to a
constant we can work out how it how it
behaves I think the distance grows
logarithmically the distance grows
logarithmically with time oh so it's
Unbound yeah the distance is unbounded
Unbound yeah but the velocity goes to
zero the velocity is Astic to zero
whereas if the energy is positive the
velocity is ASM totic to something
greater than zero right
exactly that's
correct okay
before settling on K let's plug into
this
equation row =
m/ a cubed and M is just a
parameter it's a parameter that has to
be determined by uh by observation if
you like right then this equation
becomes
M and it's not the mass of the Sun and
it's not the mass of the Galaxy it's
just the mass in the cubic region of
space one unit on a side divided by a
cubed and that's it that is the fredman
Robertson Walker equation the so-called
matter dominated case we'll we we'll
explain what that means later okay what
about K we can make various choices the
simplest choice is k equals
z that's the case where everything is
exactly at the escape Velocity
and it's simpler only in that the
mathematics is simpler if I said k equal
to Z it's obviously simpler there are
fewer terms in the equation that's all
equations are easier to solve so I'm
going to take you through the
solution of the equations in the
specially easy case where K is equal to
zero that's just at the critical
velocity we'll see what
happens okay so let's rewrite it
a do over
a
squared is equal to 8 Pi
mg / 3 a
sar a cubed excuse me a
cubed period that's it when K is equal
to zero the equations with K are a
little
harder they're harder to solve but not
that much harder to solve okay um how am
I going to solve them I'm not going to
spend a lot of time solving different
this is a differential equation for a a
of
T the a DT is equal to no it is what it
is what it is I'm going to solve it by
guessing the answer and then showing you
that it solves the equation this is one
way of solving the equation right uh if
you
this is the way people usually solve
equations and then
they all
right we could try various things we
could try a is a power law we could try
an exponential we could try all sorts of
interesting functions a power law is
usually the first thing you try the
power law means that
a increases or decreases incidentally
okay okay now we can uh now we can see
something
interesting the right hand side here is
never zero and it's always
positive the left hand
side is always obviously positive it's a
square of something but it but it could
become zero how could it become zero if
the universe expanded and then Rec
contracted at exactly the point where it
turns around a DOT would be zero
right but the right hand side is not
zero never zero so that means this
universe cannot turn around and contract
either it's growing or it's shrinking
and it stays that way forever it either
is eternally growing or eternally
shrinking Well it can't eternally shrink
because it'll shrink to a point but it
can eternally grow and that means that a
do over a is
positive uh it means the universe grows
forever
all right let's try let's try some
things how about a grows like
T A is proportional to T there's a
possible answer well it won't work but
let's Jazz it up a little bit uh we
could try t^2 we could try T cubed we
could try t to the 4 9ths we could try t
to the pi power we could try all sorts
of things let's just call it t to the
power p and try to figure out what P has
to be to solve the equation
h
no let's also be a little more
General how about putting some constant
unknown constant
there and see if we can plug this
formula into the equation and determine
what the two unknown constants are and
check that the equation is solved by
those Unknown by those appropriate
constants
that is the way I am quite certain this
equation was solved the first time just
try some simple solution this is a very
simple thing to start with uh and it is
the solution of the equation with
appropriate values of p and C so let's
try it first of all what is a
DOT the time derivative of
a all we have to do is differentiate
this the C by assumption now as a
constant it work out that you can't
solve the equation this way then you
have to stop modifying but let's check a
DOT is equal to c p t to the P minus one
right everybody agree with
that okay what about a DOT over
a a DOT over
a let's divide by a a is CT to the
P well first of all the C's the constant
C cancels out that's
nice it'll come
back that cancels out what is T to the p
minus1 over t to the
P one over T the p is the T to the p is
cancel and you just left with t theus1
which is 1/
T that's a do over
a it's always proportional to one / t
with the power LW
the power enters just in the numerator
here very simply okay let's write down
the equation now a do over a 2 that's
p^2 over T ^2
right p^2 over t^2 on the left side of
the equation
equals 8 Pi
mg divided by three and
now see
cubed t to the 3
p all right I've just cubed a a is C
cubed * t^ 3
p okay that goes here a cubed is C cubed
T to 3
p first question can the left hand side
and the right hand side be possibly be
the same how can it be that what
something which goes as 1 over t^2 can
also go on the right hand side as 1 over
t^ the 3
p p is 2/3 2/3 yeah that's the only way
so the first thing we find out is that
this equation can only be solved if
p is equal to two two uh 2/3 yeah 2/3 if
p is
2/3 then what appears here is just t^2
in the denominator same as the t^2 here
so that's the first piece of information
we learn that the Universe
expands as the 2/3 power
of of time it doesn't expand linearly
with time a growing like T that would be
sort of unaccelerated
motion it expands less rapidly than that
in fact it slows down somewhat so it's t
so we can now replace T by 2/3
everywhere
is well if we choose T to be 2/3 then
the time dependence on both sides of the
equation is the same that's been
guaranteed and so I can cancel the time
dependence t to the 3 p just becomes
t^2 and I can now cancel it
and lo and behold I have a formula now t
p^ s is what 4
9ths p^2 is 4
9th and now I can solve this equation
for the unknown constant
C what is it C
cubed is equal to 9 * 8 is 72 well 9 * 8
9 * 8
Pi
mg ultip by 9 /
4 have I left any uh is that
it three on the
bottom 9 * 8 / 4 * 3 is
6 so
I then determine
C it's
guaranteed that the equation is
solved by this assumption a
equal 6 Pi m
g the cube root of
that that's the cube root of that that's
a does it solve the equation you can
check that it solves equation but you'll
just be going back through the same
steps that we did okay it does solve the
equation in fact it's the only solution
of the
equation the only solution of the
equation and it tells you the most
interesting thing that it tells you is
that the Universe continues to expand
expands as the 2/3 power of
uh uh of
time okay shouldn't there be an unknown
con
yeah uh the unknown constant can be
absorbed into a shift of what you call T
equal Z notice that a t equals 0 the
scale factor goes to zero the unknown
constant whenever you have yeah there is
an unknown constant but you can put it
into the form T minus some t0 to the uh
uh
2/3 that becomes the unknown constant
but then it's just a shift of what you
call T equals z that's the only uh
that's the only unknown
constant so once you say that t equal 0
corresponds to the time at which a is
equal to zero there's no more constants
left all right well first of all among
other things it tells us that if we go
back in time to a certain
time a some T namely T equals 0 a will
be equal to0 a equals z is this crazy
condition where everything is squashed
on top of everything else and the
density becomes
infinite so if you like the time and
that of course is what we refer to is
the Big Bang the Big Bang is when
a to say zero is probably extreme we
don't know what happens to matter when
it gets too dense but at some time a was
so small that everything was so crowded
that uh that um atoms were crowded on
top of atoms nuclei where quarks crowded
on top of quarks and it was a solid
dense uh
configuration that's time T equals z
when the scale factor is zero this T
here is the time from that particular
era when things were very very
crowded okay now this as I said first of
all this is a model that does not
capture some of the physics it captures
some Physics not all of it but but it
captures enough to uh to note some
interesting fact um let's come back over
to
here a do over a is the Hubble constant
that's the Hubble
constant on the right hand side we have
2/3
T now as has been pointed out the Hubble
constant depends on time yes it does
here it is how does it depend on time
like one over the time
but here's a tool that you can now use
the Hubble constant
today is one 2 / 3 times the age of the
universe that's what T is T is the time
from The Big Bang and the Hubble
constant is simply almost just one over
the age of the
universe approximately apart from this
factor of 2/3 the Hubble con an is one
over the age of the
universe the age of the
universe so if we know the Hubble
constant
today we can tell what the age of the
universe is or at least we can trace it
back to the point where our equations
might not make sense because they're too
Newtonian they don't take into account
quantum mechanics when matter gets very
close together new things happen but we
can trace it back as far as the
equations make sense and say how long
ago was the universe
ejected uh from this very very dense
State all right we measure the Hubble
constant we know what the Hubble
constant is just by astronomically
measuring the distance and the velocity
of distant galaxies I never remember
what the Hubble constant is in uh in any
kind
of uh what what what are the units it's
um uh meter uh meters per second per
second no meters per second per
kilometer no meters per it's given in
ridiculous units uh astronom is crazy
units what I do remember is the age of
the
universe right right what I do remember
is easier for me to remember the age of
the universe than the Hubble constant as
given in astronomer peculiar units um
Kil a parex per per something per
something and uh uh what is the age of
the universe again it's measured by
measuring the Hubble constant distance
and velocity and the answer is give or
take uh few
years uh 13 billion years what some
between 13 and 14 billion years you said
k z that's pretty realistic uh it's
pretty good yep very realistic in fact
we measure we measure that constant K in
um microwave and isotropy experiments
and to the best of uh any measurement at
the present time K is zero it's zero to
within about
1% okay uh but that's
h no no no no the 1% is a Bound in other
words we know that it's not bigger than
1% it's not bigger than one that that's
small
uh and we're going to talk about what K
really means but uh but
uh let's put it this way high Precision
cosmology and it is now a reasonably
High Precision subject is still
consistent with K being zero there's no
known deviation from k equals zero yeah
uh the reasons for that yeah okay I'm
still confused about what m is it was
the mass inside an arbitrary volume
arbitrary yeah so so we ought to come
back to what's to a right right right a
also has a degree of
arbitrariness
why
because there's a arbitrariness on both
sides the real thing which is not
arbitrary is a all right a
/ M the 1/3
all right now why why is this particular
combination the physically relevant or
physically meaning meaningful
uh what is
a a depends on your choice of initial
grid I could have taken this
box to be the distance from us to
Andromeda I could have taken it to be
the distance from us to the coma cluster
or
whatever
uh the equations are always the same but
the amount of
matter within a box depends on which box
I
choose right supposing I double the size
of the box of my um let's call it the
fiducial box supposing I double the size
of this basic box what happens to M
inside it it gets multiplied by eight
right
right what happens to a / M the
1/3 it doesn't
change okay so this is really the
quantity which um is independent of your
choice of conventions for how you choose
the grid double the size of the grid a
becomes only half as big as it
was is that right no double the size of
the grid a a doubles I'm sorry double
the size of the grid a
doubles the mass goes up by a factor of
eight but the mass to the 1/3 goes up by
a factor of
two so this is the form this is the
quantity which is independent of the
choice of grid does that answer your
question it confused me now about what I
thought a was a is arbitrary to some
extent a is arbitrary
a m 13 is a a m 1/3 is related to m/ a
cubed is it not yeah right this is the
density and that's the thing which is
physical that's the thing which has real
physical
meaning uh the amount of mass within uh
well not a x
right no M was defined to be the mass
within a unit box an a box yeah with an
a CU box right okay so it is the real
physical density of matter this here is
uh and it's and
it's
um right it does change with time of
course it changes with time it grows
like T to the
2/3 but at any given time this quantity
is independent of the way you choose the
grid but going to use a to compute the
age of the universe you need to have a
number for
M no actually you
don't we here's what we discovered quite
apart from what m is quite apart from
what m is we always found that P was 2/3
right that was independent of M so that
says that a is equal to some unknown
constant the unknown constant C depends
on
M right C * T
2/3 okay the unknown constant C cancels
out of the age of the universe a DOT is
equal to
2/3 C * tus 1/3 is that
right I've just differentiated it the
Hubble constant which is a do over a is
just 2 over3 T the con here cancels out
the constant cancels out and with it
cancels out the dependence on
M so it's quite remarkable that the
calculation of the age of the universe
doesn't depend on the density of
mass at least the calculation in terms
of the connection with the Hubble
constant the connection between the age
of the universe and the Hubble constant
and so
forth is independent of uh
of because is that sort of because uh
the Big Bang happened such that the k
equals zero and then therefore we can
now ignore C I mean uh it all cancels if
K was different from zero then then it
would then it would be a little bit of
dependence yeah yeah yeah that's right
if K was not zero there would be a
littleit
this when was
the when was it when was M when did they
publish it well
fredman was killed during World War
I Einstein invented the general theory
of relativity around 1915 that doesn't
leave much of a window somewhere is in
there everybody know when World War I
was end in 1918 yeah so so right now
fredman didn't have all of this uh quite
uh as in the form that I I have it
exactly the history beyond that I don't
know I don't know who fredman and
Robertson Walker were uh I'm sorry I
don't know who um Robertson and Walker
were I'm not sure I'm sure they played
some some key role in putting some of
these
together uh this all seems to depend on
an assumption of an open universe is
what yes it uh it depends on the
universe being
flat I've used I've used flat geometry
flat spatial
geometry we're going to come to
that we're going to come to that the
three
possibilities k equals positive negative
or zero correspond to Flat
space uh k equal negative is negative
curved space and k equal positive is
positive curved space so that does
depend on the universe being
flat yeah
uh I want oh I want really really in
this form I suspect that the history uh
really doesn't go back past the
acceptance of The Big Bang Theory which
was sometime in the 60s in this precise
form this form has been sort of set up
to be useful it's been set up to be
useful you the things that are in it are
the density of matter the scale factor
how much of it uh fredman actually wrote
down I don't
know yeah the flatness of I mean you
start off by talking about flat space
and you use that assumption in
estimating the density well of course I
didn't say flat space I said Newtonian
Newtonian but of course space is flat in
Newtonian physics right so if it weren't
flat there you have to make some
adjustments to the equation
nope interesting all you have to do is
put K in back in either positive
negative or zero that's all it takes
that's all it takes the equation itself
now I can I'll I'll explain why in a
second let me get one more question why
why there should be an equation based on
Newtonian physics that should have uh
the full
complexity
uh it's an interesting uh question but
uh yeah
um right now you said that the length of
meter scks doesn't depend on
a at sometime long ago did the length of
meter sticks depend on a
well sufficiently long ago I suppose the
meter sticks were so crowded together
that they melted and blended into each
other and uh the idea of a meter stick
uh sure at some point the meter sticks
were just about a meter apart a little
before that they were pushing against
the each other and got
squeezed uh we're assuming they
perfectly rigid yeah there's no such
thing as a rigid body in in
relativity remember that you remember
why there can't be a rigid body if there
was a truly rigid body and you hit it on
this side since its length can't change
the other side would instantaneously
have to move off but the in but but if
that were true then you could send
messages faster than the speed of light
so the other side can't move till light
has a chance to get there and so you
know there's no such thing as a truly
rigid
body what why do you think there is this
uh Coincidence of which Coincidence of
of equation neonian and relativistic ah
well all right here I think is what you
can say um when do you expect general
relativity to become important in this
particular kind of analysis I'm not
going to pick that up uh
it's when the curvature of space becomes
when the curvature becomes
important
um it's kind of like the earth when does
the earth when does the uh curvature of
the earth become important when you're
studying regions of the earth which are
of order of magnitude the radius of the
Earth if you study a small little patch
of Earth then you needn't uh worry about
uh the curvature of the earth now
supposing we're interested in the
question how does grass
grow do we have to worry about the
curvature of the earth to figure out the
the principles of the growing of grass
no why because grass is the distance
between little bits of grass is a lot
lot smaller than the radius of curvature
of the
earth um as long as we're studying
cosmology on distance scales smaller
than the radius of curvature of the
whole universe that's supposed to be the
whole
universe thought of as a giant
three-dimensional sphere or something
else we can still study little portions
of it which may have many many many
galaxies and the study of a little
portion of it on a scale smaller than
the total radius of
curvature will it will be a good
approximation and and the smaller the
region the better the approximation we
can do it by Newtonian mechanics
Newtonian mechanics assumes two things
okay it assumes two things the first
thing is
that uh the curvature of
space is on the whole is not important
in the problem that's get that gets rid
of general relativity the second thing
is nothing is moving very fast near the
speed of light now as long as I study a
small enough
region and use the Hubble law that
velocity is Hubble time
distance as long as the distance is not
so large that the velocity gets up near
the speed of light then the equations
that we written down are correct well
the equations we wrote down gave us an
answer and you can think of that answer
as how as how um the scale factor
evolves with time as seen by only
looking you know if the Earth were to
suddenly start
expanding uh uniformly and we go out in
a field we could measure the precise
behavior of the expansion of the radius
of the Earth without ever measuring the
radius of the Earth itself and without
even realizing that the uh Earth was
curved we would just watch how the grass
blades uh increase the distance between
them so as long as the distance is small
enough that the relative distance
between Blades of grass doesn't grow
with the speed of light and as long as
the curvature of the earth is not
important we can study things in the
small and
uh that's what this is this is the study
of cosmology on distant scales small
enough that we don't get near the speed
of light and small enough so that the
curvature radius of curvature is
important
does our hble volume meet both of those
meets the first right as far as we know
the only thing that's important is that
there be a
scale which is big enough so that things
are homogeneous and small enough so that
curvature and velocity are not
depreciable all right so there is such a
scale a few million light years on a
side where the speed of uh re receding
velocities is still much smaller than
the speed of light and in which it's
still much much smaller than the radius
of
curvature so we just take that region
and we study it and we say it's good
enough to do it by theoni
physics that H just to be considered
Conant
doesn't eventually but as long as we
study things on smaller scales than that
we're okay yep we go out far enough and
things will be receding with a speed of
light yeah but that doesn't explain why
there's a term in this Newtonian
equation that represent that it
corresponds to
curvature ah there is a
right right we'll get there we'll get
there we'll get there next time next
time we'll talk about
curvature we'll talk about the curvature
of space and we'll talk about um
Einstein's equations and the relation
between Einstein's equations and
Newton's
equations basically as you might
expect plus or minus I can't remember uh
k / a s this is one of the Einstein
equations uh here let's let's just look
at it k k uh is a
number K is a number a pure number
okay so a DOT over a 2ar minus K over a
2 this has to do with geometry it has to
do with how the universe is expanding it
has to do with the metric a is connected
with the metric of space so it's on the
left hand side I've transposed this to
the left hand side over
here plus or minus probably Plus what's
on this side here has to do with
geometry the geometry of expansion
what's on the right hand side has to
do with energy density M A cubed well
why am I writing an m a cub it's a pi G
time the energy density why energy
density mass and energy are the same
thing this is clearly one of the
Einstein equations that connects on the
leftand side geometry with the right
hand side which is energy density
right so another way to derive exactly
the same equation is to write down the
Einstein equations and simply plug in
our assumptions our assumptions
homogeneous uniformly expanding
uh yeah plug
in this
metric with an arbitrary time with an
arbitrary time dependence calculate the
curvature calculate the Einstein tensor
put it on the left side side on the
right hand side put the energy density
and that becomes Einstein's equations so
and that's I think that's the way the
equations were first discovered not by I
think it was as far as I know it was it
came later that people interpreted these
equations in terms of Newton's equations
I think I'm not sure my history there
but uh uh I believe that's the case that
they first were derived from general
theory
any other
questions okay we'll see you next week
[Music]